A Register of the Peter Hannaford Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Peter Hannaford Papers
1949-2014
83094
Hoover Institution Archives
24 manuscript boxes (9.6 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the political career of Ronald Reagan as governor of California and as presidential candidate in 1976 and 1980. Includes drafts of the book by Peter Hannaford, The Reagans: A Political Portrait (New York, 1983), and research material used for the book, including speeches by Ronald Reagan; schedules, press releases, and position papers prepared for Reagan; and selected records of work for Reagan carried out by the public relations firm Deaver & Hannaford, Inc.
Hannaford, Peter D.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Chronology
1932 September 21 Born, Glendale, California
1954 AB, University of California
1954-1956 First Lieutenant, Signal Corps, U.S. Army
1956 Account executive, Helen A. Kennedy advertising firm
1957-1962 Vice president, Kennedy-Hannaford, Inc., San Francisco and Oakland, California
1962-1967 President, Kennedy-Hannaford, Inc. (name changed to Kennedy, Hannaford & Dolman, Inc., 1965)
1967-1969 Pettler and Hannaford, Inc.
1968-1969 National president, Mutual Advertising Agency Network
1969-1972 Vice president, Wilton, Coombs & Colnett, Inc.
1972 Representative nominee, United States Congress
1972-1973 Chairman, California Governor's Consumer Fraud Task Force
1973 President, Hannaford & Associates, Oakland, California
1974 Assistant to Governor of Californis – Director, Public Affairs, Governor's office, Sacramento, California
1975-1995 Chairman of the Board, Hannaford Company, Inc.
1981-1989 Trustee, White House Preservation Fund
1981-1992 Trustee, Public Relations Advertising Commission, USIA
1983 Author, The Reagans: A Political Portrait
1986 Author, Talking Back to the Media (Japanese edition, 1990)
1986-1991 Member, The Commonwealth Fund's Commission on Elderly People Living Alone
1991-1996 Member, Advertising Commission, Mount Vernon
1994 Co-author, Remembering Reagan
1996 Managing Director, Franklin Firm, Washington, D.C.
1997 Editor, My Heart Goes Home: A Hudson Valley Memoir by Thomas Sweet Lossing
1999 Compiler and editor, The Essential George Washington
2001 Compiler and editor, The Quotable Calvin Coolidge
Scope and Content of Collection
The Peter Hannaford papers reflect the contributions made by him and public relations firm, Deaver & Hannaford, Inc., to the development of Ronald Reagan's political career from governor of California to his candidacy for the presidency of the United States in 1976 and 1980. This process is based on an extensive search for research materials, such as Ronald Reagan's correspondence, schedules, writings and speeches, that Peter Hannaford used in his books including, The Reagans: A Political Portrait, and is evident in the entire collection.
The Peter Hannaford File, on the one hand, is a documentation about his literary accomplishments and his plan for promoting his books through public events, book tours, radio interviews, and radio scripts, and on the other, represents his efforts to develop a positive political image of Ronald Reagan.
The Ronald Reagan File sheds light on the campaigns of 1976 and 1980, to focus attention on campaign issues, represent the Republican political platform, and bring to the forefront the organized and systematic effort made to reflect on Ronald Reagan's stand on the issues and their impact on the primary elections.
Collected Research series is basically a collection of research materials intended to gather information relating to conference proceedings attended by Ronald Reagan as governor of California, countries, individuals, national policies, organizations, political parties, and visit of foreign dignitaries signifying possible impact on United States foreign policy. Although the dates of this series have been quoted as 1949-1980, there are photocopies of materials about Panama Canal dating back to 1901.
The Photographs and slides play an important role as they depict campaign trips and are a visual representation of Ronald Reagan, Peter Hannaford, Margaret Thatcher, and others. Audio-Visual File consists of one 7 inch 45 RPM record illustrating Ronald Reagan's commentary on current issues affecting our lives and 4 cassettes recording voices of some prominent politicians and media personalities. This could complement Ronald Reagan's speeches on the campaign trail.
Last but not the least, the Computer Files consists of 6 disks serving as an electronic storage for manuscripts of Peter Hannaford's books and related papers, either written or edited by him.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 6 series: Peter Hannaford File, Ronald Reagan File, Collected Research, Photographs, Audio-Visual File, and Computer File.
Related Material
Deaver and Hannaford, Inc. Hoover Institution Archives
Ronald Regan Subject Collection, Hoover Institution Archives
To see a complete listing of all the related collections, please go to Hoover Institution Archives catalog web site at http://library.stanford.edu/socrates and use the search term Reagan, Ronald
Reagan, Ronald.; California--Politics and government--1951-; Conservatism.; Presidents--United States--Election--1976.; Presidents--United States--Election--1980.; Reagan, Nancy, 1923-.; United States--Politics and government.
- Peter Hannaford File, 1949-2005. (Box 1-5)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, memoranda, notes, promotional materials, and writings, documenting Peter Hannaford's literary accomplishments and methods of publicity, as well as his involvement in developing Ronald Reagan's political image, arranged alphabetically by physical form and then in chronological order. Additional information may be found in Ronald Reagan File
  - Correspondence, 1974-2000 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Memoranda, 1974-1983 and undated (Folder 1: 2)
  - Notes, 1974-1983 and undated (Folder 1: 3)
  - Writings
    - Articles
      - American Prowler. Org., 2002-2003 (Folder 1: 4-5)
      - American Spectator On Line, 2000-2005 (Folder 1: 6-8)
      - Ferndale, California Enterprise, 1994-1995 (Folder 1: 9)
      - Northern Sentinel Columns, 1992-1995 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Books
      - The Reagans: A Political Portrait, 1983
        - Chapters
          - I-IV (Folder 1: 11)
          - V-VIII (Folder 1: 12)
          - IX-XI. (Folder 1: 13)
            Includes epilogue
      - Talking Back to the Media (TBTTM), 1986 (Box 2)
        - General
          - Manuscript, undated, and printed copy, 1986 (Folder 2: 1)
          - Japanese Edition, 1990 (Printed copy) and related materials, 1985-1996 (Folder 2: 2)
        - Correspondence
          - General correspondence, 1983-1991 (Folder 2: 3)
          - Book promotion, 1985-1988 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
        - Promotional materials File
          - General, 1986. (Folder 2: 5)
            Includes information about dealing with the press
          - Author event, 1986 (Folder 2: 6)
          - Book tours
            - Los Angeles, 1986 March 8- September (Folder 2: 7)
            - Eureka, 1986 March 18 – April 20 (Folder 2: 8)
            - New York, 1986 March 19 –May 13 and undated (Folder 2: 9)
            - Sacramento, 1986 March 19 – April 22 (Folder 2: 10)
            - Kansas City, 1986 April 10 – 15 and undated (Folder 2: 11)
          - Radio interviews, 1986 March 25 – June 19 and undated (Folder 2: 12)
          - Research materials for the book, 1969-1985 and undated (Box-folder 3: 1-9)
        - Reviews
          - 1983-1991 (Box-folder 4: 1)
          - 1986-1991 (Folder 4: 2)
      - My Heart Goes Home, edited by PeterHannaford, 1997
        - Correspondence, 1949-2000. (Folder 4: 3)
          Includes a printed copy
      - The Essential George Washington (TEGW), compiled and edited by PeterHannaford, 1999
        - Correspondence
          - 1997-1999 (Folder 4: 4)
          - 1999-2000 (Folder 4: 5)
        - Manuscript, parts I-III, undated (Folder 4: 6-8)
        - Printed and typescript copies, 1999 and undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
        - Reviews and promotional materials, 1999-2000 (Folder 5: 2)
        - Miscellany. Spring book catalog, 2000 (Folder 5: 3)
      - The Quotable Calvin Coolidge (Coolidge, TQC), compiled and edited by PeterHannaford, 2001
        - Brochures, 1999-2000 and printed copy of the book, 2001 (Folder 5: 4)
        - Correspondence
          - 2000 April – July (Folder 5: 5)
          - 2000 June – 2001 July (Folder 5: 6)
          - Miscellany, undated (Folder 5: 7)
- Ronald Reagan File, 1966-1981. (Box 6-9)
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, report, schedule, and writings and speeches relating to various campaign issues, both for 1976 and 1980 presidential elections, arranged alphabetically by physical form and then in chronological order. They represent Republican political platform, Ronald Reagan's stand on the issues, and an assessment of primary election results. Additional information may be found in Peter Hannaford File
  - Agenda, 1977 February 10 – 1980 June 25. (Folder 6: 1)
    Includes a list of individuals participating in the CFR Steering Committee meeting
  - Campaign file
    - General. Advertising group, undated (Folder 6: 2)
    - 1976
      - Republican Party platform (Folder 6: 3)
      - Republican primaries and total of popular primary vote count by states (Folder 6: 4-5)
    - 1980
      - Statement by Ronald Reagan regarding formation of the Reagan for President Committee, 1979 (Folder 6: 6)
      - Candidacy announcement. Includes a speech by Michael Landon drafted by Peter Hannaford, 1979 and undated (Folder 6: 7)
      - Election issues, 1979 and 1980 (Folder 6: 8-9)
      - Republican Party platform and Ronald Reagan's stand on issues, 1980 February – March (Folder 6: 10-11)
  - Primary election results, 1980 (Folder 6: 12)
  - Clippings, 1966-1979 (Folder 6: 13)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1979. (Folder 6: 14)
    Includes a form letter, undated
  - Memoranda, 1976-1980 (Folder 6: 15)
  - Notes, 1979 (Folder 6: 16)
  - Printed matter, 1975-1981 (Folder 6: 17)
  - Report, 1967 (Folder 6: 18)
  - Schedules, 1980-1981. (Folder 6: 19)
    Meetings with groups and individuals
  - Travel Schedules File
    - Republic of China (ROC)
      - Daily News report from Taipei provided by the Chinese Information Service, 1978 (Folder 6: 20)
      - List of clippings, 1978 (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - Program, 1978 (Folder 7: 2)
      - Miscellany, 1978 (Folder 7: 3)
    - United States
      - 1974 (Folder 7: 4)
      - 1975 (Folder 7: 5)
      - 1976
        - January – February (Folder 7: 6)
        - March (Folder 7: 7)
        - April (Folder 7: 8)
        - May (Folder 7: 9)
        - June (Folder 7: 10)
        - July – November (Folder 7: 11)
      - 1977
        - January – May (Folder 7: 12)
        - June – December (Folder 7: 13)
      - 1978
        - January – June. (Folder 7: 14)
          Includes travel to Tokyo
        - July – December (Folder 7: 15)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Writings and speeches
    - Writings
      - Magazines
        - Esquire, 1979 April 24 (Folder 8: 2)
        - ORBIS, 1977 Fall (Folder 8: 3)
      - Newspaper columns
        - Copley News Service, 1975 January - February (Folder 8: 4)
        - King Features Syndicate
          - 1977 (Folder 8: 5)
          - 1978
            - January – April (Folder 8: 6)
            - May – July (Folder 8: 7)
            - August – October (Folder 8: 8)
            - November – December (Folder 8: 9)
          - 1979 June - July (Folder 8: 10)
      - Radio commentary, 1978 (Folder 8: 11)
      - Radio programs, 1978 and undated (Folder 8: 12-13)
      - Radio scripts
        - 1976-1977 (Folder 8: 14)
        - 1978 (Folder 8: 15)
        - 1979 (Folder 8: 16)
    - Speeches (Box 9)
      - undated (Folder 9: 1)
      - 1974-1975 (Folder 9: 2)
      - 1976-1977 (Folder 9: 3)
      - 1978
        - January – April. (Folder 9: 4)
          Includes Ronald Reagan's speech to Japanese businessmen, Tokyo, Japan, 1978 April 17, and the Chinese National Association of Commerce and Industry, Taipei, Taiwan, 1978 April 21
        - May – December (Folder 9: 5)
      - 1979 January - November (Folder 9: 6)
      - 1980
        - March - August (Folder 9: 7)
        - October - November (Folder 9: 8)
      - 1981 November (Folder 9: 9)
  - Miscellany, 1974-1976 and undated (Folder 9: 10)
- Collected Research, 1949-1980 (Box 9-13)
  Research materials relating to different countries, individuals, political issues, and policies, and policies, possibly used for writing Peter Hannaford's books, and organizing Ronald Reagan's political campaigns, arranged alphabetically
  - Botswana, 1978 (Folder 9: 11)
  - Briggs' Initiative – Proposition 6, 1978 (Folder 9: 12)
  - Morocco, 1978-1979 (Folder 9: 13)
  - Most Favored Nation Status: Trade with Communist Countries, 1979 (Folder 9: 14)
  - Mozambique, 1973-1978 (Folder 9: 15)
  - Multi-National Corporations, 1975-1978 and undated (Folder 9: 16)
  - Namibia, 1978 (Folder 9: 17)
  - National Defense Strategies, 1976-1977 and undated (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
  - national Governor's Conference Proceedings, Seattle, Washington, 1974 June 2-6 (Folder 10: 3)
  - National Health Insurance, 1974-1979 (Folder 10: 4)
  - National Petroleum, 1980 (Folder 10: 5)
  - New Left, 1978 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Oil, 1975-1976 (Folder 10: 7)
  - Panama Canal, 1904-1979 and undated (Folder 10: 8-13)
  - Panama Canal, 1901-1978 and undated (Box-folder 11: 1-6)
  - Polls – College student, 1974 (Folder 11: 7)
  - Population, 1978 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Prison Reform, 1976 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, 1974-1979 (Folder 12: 2)
  - SALT II, 1977-1979 (Folder 12: 3)
  - Sears, John, undated. (Folder 12: 4)
    Report
  - Social Security, 1978 (Folder 12: 5)
  - Tax Limitation and Proposition, California, 1973-1982 and undated (Folder 12: 6-7)
  - Thatcher, Margaret, Mrs., 1975-1976 (Folder 12: 8)
  - Total Value of Public Assistance Benefits in California, 1975 (Folder 12: 9)
  - United States Labor Party (U.S. Labor Party), 1978 (Folder 12: 10)
  - USSR delegation's visit to Sacramento, 1974 (Folder 12: 11)
  - Welfare, 1974-1976 and undated (Folder 12: 12-13)
  - Welfare reform, 1971-1977 and undated (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
  - Wilson, Pete, 1975-1976 (Folder 13: 3)
- Photographs, 1974-1982 and undated (Box 13)
  23 photographic prints and 3 photographic proof sheets depicting Ronald Reagan with Margaret Thatcher and other individuals, 139 35 mm slides depicting campaign trips, news conferences, and so on, arranged chronologically
  - 13 photographic prints depicting Ronald Reagan and Margaret Thatcher, undated (Folder 13: 4)
  - 3 photographic proof sheets depicting Ronald Reagan and others, undated (Folder 13: 5)
  - 7 sheets containing 139 35mm color slides, depicting campaign trips, news conferences, different social events, bicentennial ceremony, and so on, including some taken and arranged by Peter Hannaford, 1974. (Folder 13: 6)
    Includes a note by Peter Hannaford, 1982
  - 10 photographic prints depicting Ronald Reagan with different individuals, including Richard Allen, Harry O'Connor, Irene Hannaford, Art Linkletter, busy with window shopping at Munich in 1978; at a radio recording session, 1975; and 1 print particularly selected to be included in one of Peter Hannaford's books, 1982 (Folder 13: 7)
- Audio-Visual File, 1997-1998 and undated (Box 13)
  One 7 inch 45 RPM record titled, Viewpoint with Ronald Reagan, and 4 cassettes, recordings by different individuals, arranged chronologically
  - One 7 inch 45 RPM record titled, Viewpoint with Ronald Reagan, "a commentary on the issues and events which shape our lives,", undated (Folder 13: 8)
  - 4 cassettes recording Caron Lee regarding George Washington (GW?), undated; Eugene McCarthy, undated; David McCullough, undated; and Letitia Baldridge, 1997-1998 (Folder 13: 9)
- Computer Files, 1997-2000 (Box 13)
  6 computer disks containing articles by Peter Hannaford about George Washington, manuscripts of his books, related papers, correspondence, and memoranda, arranged chronologically
  - 1 computer disk containing manuscript and related papers re My Heart Goes Home: A Hudson Valley Memoir (boyhood recollection of Thomas S. Lossing, edited by Peter Hannaford), undated (Folder 13: 10)
    Disk unreadable.
  - 2 disks re The Quotable Calvin Coolidge (TQCC) containing manuscript, memos, and correspondence, 2000 (Folder 13: 11)
    Use copies available in reading room of contents of disk labeled "Manuscript for 'The Quotable Calvin Coolidge.'" Disk labeled "related memos and correspondence" unreadable
  - 3 computer disks re The Essential George Washington (Folder 13: 12)
    - Manuscripts, Parts I, II, III – "Nuts and Bolts" sections of the text and correspondence with Peter Hannaford's editor, 1997-1999
      Use copies available in reading room.
    - Manuscript, correspondence, and related papers, 1997-1999
      Use copies available in reading room
    - Various articles about George Washington written by Peter Hannaford, undated
- Incremental Materials (Box 14-24)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu